<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Concussion Awareness and Prevention | Michelle VanTieghem</title>
    <link>/cycling_blog/</link>
      <atom:link href="/cycling_blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Concussion Awareness and Prevention</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Concussion Awareness and Prevention</title>
      <link>/cycling_blog/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three myths about concussions</title>
      <link>/cycling_blog/concussion2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/cycling_blog/concussion2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since that first accident 18 months ago, I’ve had two more crashes, and unfortunately, two more concussions. I’ll save those stories for another time.  But through all of these experiences, I learned about the common misconceptions about head injury, helmets, and concussion severity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1--you-didnt-lose-consciousness&#34;&gt;1.  You didn’t lose consciousness!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When describing my crash, the first question everyone asked me was the same: did you lose consciousness? This common assumption – that head injuries are only serious if you lose consciousness – is largely false. Loss of consciousness only occurs in about 10% of head injuries, and research is inconclusive about whether loss of consciousness actually predicts concussion severity or recovery time.  In reality, there are several other risk factors that are more important, and often over-looked. For example, even though men are twice as likely to have a head injury, women are much more likely to suffer from concussions. Likewise, prior history of head injury, and prior mental health history also influence how quickly an individual might recover from a head injury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2--your-helmet-didnt-break&#34;&gt;2.  Your helmet didn’t break!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One common misconception, which is prevalent both in the cycling community and the emergency room, is that a head injury doesn’t need to be taken seriously if you were wearing your helmet, especially if the helmet didn’t break. But the reality is that industry standards only require that a cycling helmet protects against serious traumatic brain injury, like a skull fracture. Your helmet will likely save your life, but it won’t prevent a concussion. Only recently have new helmet technologies been developed to protect against concussions, by trying to minimize the rotational forces that occur when your head makes impact.  However, these helmets are very new, and proprietary, with very little objective research (i.e. not funded by the company) that have tested their efficacy in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3--your-ct-scan-was-negative&#34;&gt;3.  Your CT scan was negative!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common test performed following a head injury is a CT scan, which is used to diagnose acute problems like intracranial bleeding that require urgent medical attention. If your doctor says the CT scan is clear, that means your helmet did its job – it prevented a life-threatening situation. However, you may still have a concussion. There are no biological or imaging tests that can diagnose a concussion. The symptoms are largely invisible, and can only be diagnosed from the patient’s own self-report (e.g. feeling foggy, irritable, dizzy, or having difficulty concentrating).  Importantly, these symptoms may not emerge until hours or days after you’ve left the emergency room. That’s why follow-up evaluations are recommended for anyone who sustains a head injury - even if you are feeling fine in the initial few days afterward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;concussion-resources&#34;&gt;Concussion Resources:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concussion signs and symptoms from the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cdc.gov/headsup/pdfs/providers/facts_about_concussion_tbi-a.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CDC&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://concussionsontario.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/dos-donts_3.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Concussion&lt;/a&gt;
 Do&#39;s and Don&#39;ts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concussion management from 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usacycling.org/coaches/resources/concussion-management&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;USA Cycling&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medicine of Cycling Traumatic Brain Injury 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medicineofcycling.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/ConcussionAssessmentChart2012.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Flow Chart&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My (first) concussion story</title>
      <link>/cycling_blog/concussion1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/cycling_blog/concussion1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is the first of a series of posts on concussions and recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was my first full season of racing, and after a couple of near-misses on the Cat 4/5 podium, it was my last chance to show off my new-found love for racing criteriums. Bored of Central Park by this late in the season, I opted to go north on the west side bike path to the less traveled Fort Tryon Park in Inwood. I did a short workout, easy openers to prep my legs for the next day’s race: Fort Lee Crit. The riding conditions were great - it had rained overnight, but the sun was out and it was such a nice day that it was hard to resist the urge to join my friends for a long ride across the GW bridge. But with my goal set on having fresh legs for the next day, I started to make my way home, thinking that I was safer on the bike path than on the roads in Washington Heights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you ever ride north of 155th St, you’ll know the bridge: the broken, run-down, wooden bridge that used to be adorned with gaping holes and giant orange cones, which crosses over the abandoned train tracks. Having ridden across a dozen times by now, I didn’t think twice as I coasted down the hill southbound, and rode onto the bridge at around 10 mph. As I carefully avoided the gaping wooden holes and orange cones, my front tire wedged between 2 planks of wet, rotten, slippery wood. I lost control of my bike, and fell toward my left side, with the side of my head being the first point of contact. Dazed, but having not lost consciousness, I lied there stunned in the middle of the bridge. A few runners who had witnessed the incident stopped to ask me if I was ok. I wasn’t sure. I was talking normally and could even get up to walk my bike to the side of the path, but they still wanted to call 911. In the 30 minutes that we waited for the ambulance, two more cyclists wiped out at the same spot on the bridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was finally at the ER, the physician’s assistant who evaluated me was not concerned about my head injury. My helmet didn’t crack. I didn’t lose consciousness. My pupils weren’t dilated, and I wasn’t vomiting, nauseous, or dizzy. I told her I had a big race the next day, and I was anxious to hear the answer: could I race? Would it be safe? She merely advised me to see how I felt. As a determined athlete, her nonchalance seemed like a green light that I was good to go. She handed me a pamphlet on how to treat road rash, and I was discharged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important thing that this doctor did not tell me is that concussion symptoms might not appear right away. In fact, they may not appear for hours or days, but could persist for weeks or months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After taking it easy the rest of the day, I woke up the next morning feeling great and ready to race. I practiced the course so much, I knew it by heart - especially the punchy hill that dropped half the field on the first lap. In the end, I got 4th place, again, but I didn’t care - I was thrilled that my crash hadn’t held me back. I was so elated on my post-race high that I did a social ride up River Road with my friends afterwards, and even PRed on Alpine! But after lunch, I was so tired that I could hardly make my way back down 9W. My boyfriend, who loves to chase after random wheels, had left me in the dust. I looked at the low numbers on my power meter and thought, damn I am tired. But that was normal after a bike race, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the next few days, things were as normal as they could be. Except, when I sat at my computer, I couldn’t keep my head up or my eyes open. With my stubborn PhD student work ethic, I tried to drag myself through the rest of the week, buying extra afternoon coffees, eager to get to the weekend stage race I had planned. Other than some mild neck whiplash and fatigue, I seemed fine. But by the weekend, I started getting head fog and dizziness on the bike. I decided I shouldn’t race, so I cheered my teammates from the sidelines. When I returned to the city on Monday, more than a week after my crash, it got worse. Daily activities, like riding the subway or working on the computer,  would trigger a headache.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My primary care doctor told me to take time off from school and recommended I see a concussion specialist. Thanks to the over-burdened healthcare system in NYC, the next available appointment wasn’t for 4 weeks. I spent the next month trying to manage my symptoms on my own. Not wanting to relent on my summer plans, I attempted a beach vacation, a bachelorette party, and an international conference, all while trying to avoid my headache triggers:  computer screens, direct sunlight, loud noise, heat, and alcohol. The subway was a nightmare, florescent lights were terrible, and bars were even worse. I would sleep 10+ hours a night, and took naps whenever I could. I wouldn’t go anywhere without Excedrin, crime podcasts, and my noise-cancelling headphones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time I had my specialist appointment a month later, my day-to-day symptoms had started to improve, but the evaluation revealed more symptoms that I had hardly noticed amid the blinding headaches. Neuropsychology testing showed small deficits in my working memory and balance. I learned that my dizziness on the bike was from the damage to my inner ear from the crash.  I started vestibular physical therapy, where I did balance exercises, and occupational therapy, where they gave me strategies to get through my work at the computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no one-size fits-all prognosis for how bad your symptoms will be after a concussion, or how quickly you’ll get better. While friends of mine have recovered from their bike-related head injuries in a few days, it took me almost 3 months to fully recover.  I stayed on the indoor trainer for weeks until I was finally ready to bike outside again. Eventually, and very slowly, I got better, and I learned a lot about concussions in the process.  The goal of this blog series is to help educate other cyclists about concussions, and the common misconceptions surrounding them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concussion Resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concussion signs and symptoms from the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cdc.gov/headsup/pdfs/providers/facts_about_concussion_tbi-a.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CDC&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://concussionsontario.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/dos-donts_3.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Concussion&lt;/a&gt;
 Do&#39;s and Don&#39;ts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concussion management 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usacycling.org/coaches/resources/concussion-management&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;USA Cycling&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
