<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Portfolio | Michelle VanTieghem</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Portfolio</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Portfolio</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Dashboard</title>
      <link>/project/data-dashboard/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/data-dashboard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal of this study is to understand the impact of the covid-19 pandemic on maternal health and well-being. New and expecting mothers shared their experiences on perinatal health care, employment, family life, and social support during the pandemic, and how they are coping with those challenges.
Using R shiny, I created an interactive data dashboard to share key findings with our collaborators, partnering clinicians, and the general public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work was done during my Post-Doc in the Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, NYU Langone Health&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting age from brain imaging data</title>
      <link>/project/age-brain-prediction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/age-brain-prediction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;under construction!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early experience and brain development</title>
      <link>/project/adversity-brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/adversity-brain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;phd-thesis-research&#34;&gt;PhD Thesis Research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my dissertation, I examined how patterns of brain development are influenced by exposure to early adversity. I leveraged existing dataset of repeated structural MRI in youth with and without exposure to early adversity (i.e., institutional care). For this analysis, I focused on two key brain regions linked to mental health risk and early adversity: the amygdala and hippocampus. First, I explored non-linearity in brain development by comparing linear, quadratic, and piecewise effects of age on structural brain volume. Then I compared these patterns between adversity-exposed and non-exposed groups. I found that early adversity was associated with &lt;em&gt;reduced growth rate&lt;/em&gt; of the amygdala and &lt;em&gt;reduced size&lt;/em&gt; of the hippocampus across age. These findings are presented in a pre-print manuscript currently under review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work was conducted in the Developmental Affective Neuroscience Lab,
Department of Psychology, Columbia University&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forecasting tool for longitudinal studies</title>
      <link>/project/study-forecast/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/study-forecast/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;interactive-web-application-for-developmental-researchers&#34;&gt;Interactive web application for developmental researchers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Longitudinal research studies aim to collect data from the same participants over time to measure developmental milestones of interest. Because these studies involve research visits at multiple age-points, they present challenges for project management across long timescales (e.g. 5 years). The optimal study design must be balanced with logistical constraints of the research team, and the burden on participants. Many variables are considered when designing a longitudinal study, from the number of participants per visit, the time intervals between visits, the target age of participants at each visit, and the total duration of the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I developed interactive tool to visualize how these variables influence the timing and volume of study visits. The web application pulls source data that the researcher provides, which includes study cohort numbers, participant age, and enrichment variables of interest. The output includes summary metrics of the selected sample and figures/tables to visualize the projected volume and timing of research visits over the selected study duration. The researcher can modulate the output to visualize how changes to study design (e.g. number of participants) impact the study schedule. Once the study design has been selected, the output tables can then be used by project managers to effectively plan study operations on a weekly basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work was done during my Post-Doc in the Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, NYU Langone Health&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
