<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Michelle VanTieghem</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Dashboard</title>
      <link>/project/data-dashboard/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/data-dashboard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During my post-doctoral fellowship at NYU Langone Health, I worked on a research project that assessed the impact of the covid-19 pandemic on maternal health and well-being.  New and expecting mothers shared their experiences during the covid-19 pandemic and how they are coping with those challenges. These data were collected via remote surveys from women in the NYC metropolitan area from April - July 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to facilitate rapid dissemination of our research relating to Covid-19, I used R shiny to develop an interactive 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://mvantieghem.shinyapps.io/cope_data_dashboard/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;data dashboard&lt;/a&gt;
 that displays key findings from this study. We show how the covid-19 pandemic has impacted various aspects of women&#39;s lives, from major changes to perinatal healthcare, to their concerns about disruptions to social, economic, and family life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code and analyses 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mvantieghem/cope_study_dashboard&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information on the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.babybees.org/cope-study&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cope Study&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early experience and brain development</title>
      <link>/project/adversity-brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/adversity-brain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;phd-thesis-research&#34;&gt;PhD Thesis Research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my graduate research, I studied the role of early experiences on brain maturation and later mental health risk. My dissertation research used structural MRI to identify how patterns of brain development differed following exposure to early adversity. I focused on brain regions that are important for processing emotions (amygdala and hippocampus) and implicated in mental health risk. My research showed that exposure to early adversity was linked to differences in the size and growth of these brain regions across childhood and adolescence. Importantly, these neurobiological changes were also associated with increased anxiety and depressive symptoms. These findings contribute to the body of knowledge idenifying how early adverse experiences can &amp;lsquo;get under the skin&amp;rsquo; to influence long-term health outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These findings are presented in a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/9au4v/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;pre-print manuscript&lt;/a&gt;
 currently under review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work was conducted in the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://danlab7.wixsite.com/mysite&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Developmental Affective Neuroscience Lab&lt;/a&gt;
,
Department of Psychology, Columbia University.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forecasting tool for longitudinal studies</title>
      <link>/project/study-forecast/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/study-forecast/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;interactive-web-application-for-developmental-researchers&#34;&gt;Interactive web application for developmental researchers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In developmental psychology, it&#39;s common to collect data from the same participants over time to measure developmental milestones of interest. These longitudinal studies involve research visits at multiple time points, presenting challenges for project management across long timescales. The optimal study design to answer a given research question must be balanced with logistical constraints of the research team, and the time burden placed on participating families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many variables are considered when designing a longitudinal study:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;total number of participants (50, or 500?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;total duration of the study (e.g. 6 months or 6 years?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;target age of participants at each visit (newborn, 12 months, 5 years?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;target populations of interest (e.g. low vs. high SES?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I developed an 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://mvantieghem.shinyapps.io/longitudinal_study_forecasting&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;interactive tool&lt;/a&gt;
 to facilitate study planning for longitudinal research studies. It&#39;s specifically geared towards research groups with existing pregnancy cohorts that plan to conduct infant follow-up assessments (e.g. newborn, 6-month and 12-month). Given how rapidly infants reach developmental milestones, the timing of study assessments is extremely important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web application, developed with R shiny, allows the researcher to provide their own source data for their unique study cohort, and see how study decisions impact the long-term study forecast. The source data includes birth dates (or due dates), and any enrichment variables relevant to that cohort (e.g. income brackets). The user can then interactively change the total number of participants to be included, time intervals between visits,  target age of participants at each visit, and the total duration of the study. The output provides summary metrics, with figures to vizualize the projected volume of study visits over time. Once the study design has been selected, the output tables can then be used by project managers to effectively plan study operations and study budgets on a weekly basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work was done during my Post-doctoral fellowship at NYU Langone Health.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
